Guide to the American Revolutionary War Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
American Revolutionary War collection
1775-1786
MS 674
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
An artificial collection of correspondence, payrolls, pay tables, receipts, commissions, and miscellanea including documents from Connecticut, Massachusetts, New York, and South Carolina military forces.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
An artificial collection of correspondence, payrolls, pay tables, receipts, commissions, and miscellanea including documents from Connecticut, Massachusetts, New York, and South Carolina military forces.
Connecticut -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Great Britain -- Colonies -- America; Massachusetts -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- History -- 1783-1815; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Bragg, Thomas, 1810-1872; Chittenden, William; Edwards, Pierpont, 1750-1826; Hazard, Stanton; Howell, Thomas, 1719-1797; Huntington, Jedediah, 1743-1818; McKinnon, John; Munson, Ezra; Parsons, Samuel Holden, 1737-1789; Peters, Richard, 1743-1828; Phillips, William, 1731?-1781; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829; Platt, Epenetus; Richards, Guy, 1747-1825; Shuldham, Molyneux, 1717?-1798; Smith, George, 1713-1776; Trumbull, Jonathan, 1710-1785; Massachusetts Infantry. 1st Regt., 1779; Massachusetts Infantry. 6th Regt., 1780
- Inventory
  - Ralph Pomeroy Papers; folders 1-9; Folio
    - Payroll of sundry persons employed in Public Services by Ralph Pomeroy, Deputy Quarter Master, 1781 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Account, as Deputy Quarter Master General, with the state of Connecticut from 1781 Jan to 1786 Jan. With a note on currency problems, and the method of payment: "...in part by State Notes received for sale of powder..." Initialed "RP" and dated "1791 Sep 5." (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Circular letters, as "Commissioner of Cloathing Accounts of U.S. Board of War," to Connecticut authorities (1 p.). Philadelphia, 1779 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Huntington, Jedidiah (1743-1818), ALS congratulating Pomeroy "on the Capture of Lord Cornwallis and his Army...about 8,000 including Tories and Negroes..." (1 p.). Peekskill, 1781 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Mix, John, ALS, transmitting a letter from "General Washington ordering the Chain of Expresses to be discharged..." (1 p. [enclosure wanting]). Newburgh, 1782 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Parsons, Samuel Holden (1737-1789), ALS, an order to "appoint officers in different parts of the State to receive and forward Recruits..." with a description of desirable and disqualifying characteristics ([2] p. on one leaf). Camp, n.p., 1781 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Peters, Richard (1744-1828), DS, commission of Ralph Pomeroy "to settle and pay all arrearages of cloathing due to the troops of these States for the year 1777" ([2] p. on one leaf). New London, 1779 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Pickering, Timothy (1745-1829), 5 ALS relating to finances and provisions for the troops, with one letter requesting that Pomeroy forward a dispatch from Count Rochambeau to the Duke de Lauzun. Newburgh,; Philadelphia, 1781 February 2, 16; May 7, 221782 March 26 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Richards, Guy (1747-1825), ALS (as Deputy Quarter Master) forwarding a Resolve for an "additional sum of #250 in Pay-Table Orders..." (1 p. [enclosure wanting]). New London, 1781 December 6 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Trumbull, Jonathan (1710-1785), 3 ALS concerning provision of troops and related finances. (1 p. with wrapper and portion of seal, 2 p. address on each verso). Lebanon, 1781 January 24; 1781 November 26; 1781 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - U.S. Treasury Dept. Pay Table Office. DS (contemporary copy), account with Ralph Pomeroy for the period 1781 Jan 27-1783 Sep 1. Signed: William Denning (2 p. on 1 leaf, folio; on verso: "The within is a true Copy of the Original lodged on file in the Office this day. Oliver Wolcott...Mar 26, 1787."). New York, 1785 December 28 (Box 2)
  - Shuldham, Molyneux Shuldham (1717?-1798), baron
    - Papers, correspondence and reports to Lord Shuldham related to his office as vice-admiral and commander-in-chief of British ships in North America, including accounts of the movements of American vessels, petitions by American prisoners and financial documents (12 items), 1777-1779 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - 2 ALS (presumably to Lord Shuldham) from an American prisoner named De La Carriere, held on board the, 1777 August 27, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anonymous
    - MS, entry in a diary by someone at Brigadier General [Selah] Heart's headquarters noting a report on British movements as given by two deserters and a visit by General Wolcott. On verso are memoranda made in Farmington, or relating to Farmington, General Heart's home ([2] p. on one leaf). Greenwich, 1779 August 16 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Platt, Captain Epenetus
    - DS, "confession" to the New Milford Committee of Inspection of "those words and actions which the Committee and others have just reason to complain of" and making retraction so that "we may no longer be Estemed Enimys to our country." With 25 additional signatures. ([2] p. on one leaf), 1775 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      General
      Historical note: Epenetus Platt was appointed captain of the first company or trainband in the town of New Milford in May 1773. In February 1781 he was imprisoned in New Gate gaol for a treasonable writing and freed in May of that year on payment of a fine and bond "for the future peacable and obedient behavior…during the present war with Great Britain."(**) In May 1786 he was released from this conviction.(***)
      (**) The Public Records of the State of Connecticut from May 1780 to October 1781…Charles J. Hoadly, compiler. Hartford, 1922. v.3, p. 433.
      (***) Ibid., v.6, p. 185.
  - Phillips, William, 1731?-1781
    - ALS to Lieutenant Collier ordering him to pay "six artificers" in Canada and Captain Craig of the Northern Army. (1 p. and accompanying outer leaf with a summary of the letter). New York, 1780 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      For additional information relating to Lieutenant Collier, see also the warrant by James Hamilton (1781 Oct 30), in box 2 (Folio)
  - Mason, Mr. and Mrs.
    - AL (in the third person) to Thomas Fayerweather asking for the loan of two pounds of pork. (1 p. with note on verso). n.p., 1779 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - McKinnon, Captain John
    - DS, memorial as Deputy Quarter Master General to Lieutenant Colonel Nisbet Balfour asking him to grant a warrant for fifteen thousand pounds. (1 p. with address portion of another leaf pasted o1 p. with address portion of another leaf pasted on). Charleston, South Carolina, 1781 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bragg, Thomas
    - Three receipts by Samuel Bridge, Enoch Coe and Ebenezer Gay to Thomas Bragg for payment received for room and board. n.p., v.p., 1780 November 11, 17, 19 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hazard, Stanton
    - ALS on leaving Hartford to Josiah Pomeroy, thanking him for "softening my captivity." (1 p.) Hartford, 1779 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - United States Lottery
    - Lottery ticket issued according to a Resolution of Congress, passed at Philadelphia, 1776 Nov 18. Signed: C. Campbell. (1 ticket: No. 42m350). n.p., undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Chittenden, William
    - ALS to the President of Congress, petitioning that body to aid the widow and children of Colonel Seth Warner who died of wounds received "in the late war." ([2] p. on 1 leaf, with thirteen signatures). Bennington, 1786 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Signers: William Chittenden, Thomas Chittenden, 1730-1797, Thomas Topman, Ethan Allen, 1738-1789, Paul Spooner, Timothy Brownson, Samuel Safford, Moses Robinson, 1742-1813, Isaac Tichenor, 1754-1838, Stephen Bendley, Gideon Brownson, Heman Smith, Samuel Canfield.
  - Munson, Ezra, et. al.
    - DS, by non-commissioned officers and soldiers of General Hazen's regiment giving Captain William Munson of Connecticut power-of-attorney to receive their wages for the period January through March 1781. (1 p. with twenty-two signatures). New Jersey, 1783 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Connecticut
    - Betts, Thaddeus, 1724-1807
      - DS, certifying as Justice of Peace to the loyalty of James K. Hallett. (1 p.) Norwalk, Connecticut, 1779 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Edwards, [Pierpont?], 1750-1826
      - MS, describing the raising of "six thousand Men," for Connecticut, their provisioning, pay, deployment and listing their officers and the system of command. ([3] p. with note on verso: Mr. Edwards Letter No. 36). n.p., [177-?] (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Howell, Thomas, 1719-1797
      - DS, attesting that John Miles of S[outh] Newhaven and his family are "thorough friends to America," and that Miner Miles never engaged in trade with Long Island. (1 p. with eleven signatures). New Haven, 1780 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Smith, George
      - DS, certifying as Judge Advocate to the Army that James K. Hallett had "supported the Character of a Friend to His Country." (1 p.). Norwich, Connecticut, 1779 February 10 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Wales, Nathanel, and Burr, Thaddeus, 1735-1801
      - ALS to an unknown recipient announcing their appointment with "Mr [Pierpont?] Edwards...a Committee to visit the Provincial Convention of New York." (1 p. with note on verso: Letter Messrs. Wales and Burr. No. 34). New York, 1775 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 22)
        See also: letter of Pierpont Edwards, No. 36
  - Massachusetts
    - Massachusetts Infantry
      - "An Abstract for Pay due to Officers and Soldiers raised for the defence of Castle and Governors Island...whereof...John Hancock is Commander...to the 31st March 1780." (1 p. folio (contemporary copy); on verso: Pay Roll Castle and Governors Island 1779-1780). n.p., [1780 March 31] (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - 1st Regt. "Size roll of the Light Infantry Company of Foot in the Massachusetts Regiment..." [giving 38 names with age, height, trade, place of origin and residence.] (1 p. folio with note on verso: Size Roll of the Light Infantry Compy in Col. Voses Regt.) n.p., 1779 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      - 6th Regt.
        - "Return of the non Commissioned Officers and Privates of Major Harwoods Company…" [giving names, rank, place of abode, dates and terms of enlistment.] ([2] p. on 2 leaves joined, with note on verso: Majors Returns for the year 1780). n.p., [1780 December 31] (Box 1, Folder 23)
        - "Return of the Non Commissioned Officers and Privates of Captain Benjamin Heywoods Company…" [giving names, rank, place of abode, dates and terms of enlistment.] ([2] p. on one leaf, folio). n.p., [1780 December 31] (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Worcester County. Certification of payments, by town, to soldiers' families, 1777 September to 1780 January. ([2] p. on one leaf). n.p., 1780 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - New York (State)
    - Dutchess County Committee. ALS to the "Committee of Safety at Newmilford" concerning William Ellis and Benjamin Ellise, who have been sent to the New Milford court. Signed: Nathan Poane [?], Chairman. (1 p. with address on verso of integral leaf). Pawling, 1776 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - U.S. Army. Continental Army. AD, "monthly Return of the Garrison of Stoney Point." Signed: B. Frothingham. ([2] p. on one leaf). Stoney Point, [N.Y.], 1782 January 28 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - South Carolina
    - Cochran, Robert. DS, Enlistment paper (printed form filled in) signed by five seamen agreeing to serve under Captain Cochran in the service of the colony of South Carolina. (1 p.) n.p., 1777 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Frederick, Colonel, [i.e. Frederic de Neuhof, 1725?-1797]. ALS to the Duke of Portland, relating to Frederick's request for payment for raising 3000 troops for the English during the American Revolution. ([3] p. on one folded leaf). London, 1783 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Hamilton, James, ca. 1710-1783. DS, warrant to Charles Bembridge, Deputy Pay Master General to His Majesty's Forces, Quebec, to pay #660. 1. 3 to David Geddes and Lieutenant Collier for sums paid to "artificers." (1 p. with summary of order on verso). New York, 1781 October 30 (Box 2)
      For additional information relating to Lieutenant Collier, see ALS by William Phillips (1780 Dec 8), in box 1, folder 14
  - Fanning, T____. ALS to Mrs. Sibel Coit describing the capture of Boston from the British on March 17, 1776. ([4] p.). Roxbury, Mass., 1776 March 22 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Dodge, Captain Barnabas (1741-1817). Orderly book kept by Dodge while serving under Major-General Robert Howe, 1732-1796, in the Hudson Highlands, New York, with court-martial accounts,. With a few pages of family accounts, 1792-1798., 1780 April 20 - June 16 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Hesse. Régiment de Losberg. Compagnie du Corps. DS, muster roll covering the period from December 25, 1781 to June 24, 1782. Signed by Major Emanuel de Wilmowsky and other officers. (3p. with docket title on p.4., from the library of Sir Thomas Phillips). Laurel Hill, Pa., 1782 July 5 (Box 2)
  - Appointment of Elisha Bostwick as Second Lieutenant of Captain Isaac Bostwick/accompanying sketch by Elisha Bostwick: facsimile, 1776 January 1 (Box 2)
  - Request for remuneration by James Hamilton, Brigadier General, 1781 October 30 (Box 2)
  - "The United States in Account with Ralph Pomeroy": handwritten copy of final settlement, Pay Table Office, 1787 March 26 (Box 2)